Last weeks video was about revisiting format level 0 from exploit-exercises/protostar on
上周的视频是关于重新访问格式的利用练习的0级/Protostar on
a modern ubuntu system.
现代Ubuntu系统。
And we played around with it to see if we can figure out a way to exploit it, but in
我们玩弄它看看可以找到利用它的方法，但是
the end I wasn’t able to solve it.
结果我没能解决。
But lucky for me a user with the name wcbowling on reddit thought it was fun too and actually
但对我来说幸运的是一个名为wcbowling的用户Reddit认为这也很有趣，事实上
had a method to exploit it.
有办法利用它。
So let’s have a look at it.
我们来看看。
So here is wcbowlings post:
下面是wcbowlings post：
I love going back to old challenged like this :) Managed to get a fairly reliable exploit,
我喜欢回到像这样被挑战的老地方：）设法获得了相当可靠的利用，
normally under 500 iterations.
通常在500次迭代下。
And there is a highlevel description on how it works:
还有一个关于如何它的工作原理是：
Overwrite the GOT entry for __stack_chk_fail with an address so we jump there instead.
覆盖\堆栈\ chk \失败的获取项有地址，所以我们跳过去。
The address can be passed in via argv, we cant use nulls but we can use blank strings
地址可以通过argv传入，我们不能使用空值，但可以使用空字符串
instead.
相反。
As the argv location is semi random, it takes around 500 iterations which is pretty reasonable
由于argv位置是半随机的，因此需要大约500次迭代，这是相当合理的
for 64bit
64位
So obviously I didn’t manage to figure that out, which means I didn’t know something
所以很明显我没想到出去，这意味着我什么都不知道
and here is a learning opportunity for me.
这是我学习的机会。
So I’m not going to pretend I knew this.
所以我不会假装我知道这些。
For whatever reason I never noticed that __stack_chk_fail is in the global offset table.
无论出于什么原因，我从来没有注意到uu stack chk fail在全局偏移量表中。
And the reason for that might be, that I never encountered a challenge with these constraints?
原因可能是，我从来没有遇到这些限制的挑战？
We have A) a format string exploit that generally allows us to write anything anywhere B)
我们有一个）格式字符串漏洞允许我们在任何地方写任何东西b）
No libc function after the format string vuln that we could overwrite in the global offset
格式字符串vuln之后没有libc函数我们可以在全局偏移中覆盖
table And C) where we also have a buffer overflow
桌子c）我们还有一个缓冲区溢出
with a stack cookie.
用一堆饼干。
So I really like this challenge now, because the solution is so clever.
所以我现在真的很喜欢这个挑战，因为解决方案是如此巧妙。
So the function that is being called when the stack cookie got overwritten through a
所以当堆栈cookie通过
buffer overflow is also on the global offset table.
缓冲区溢出也在全局偏移量上表。
Which means our goal is to redirect code execution to our winning message by overwrite the GOT
这意味着我们的目标是重定向代码执行通过覆盖got
entry for __stack_chk_fail.
_uuu stack_chk_的条目失败。
And then do a buffer overflow, to trigger that function.
然后执行缓冲区溢出，以触发那个函数。
To write to that global offset table entry, we have to get the address somewhere onto
要写入该全局偏移表条目，我们得把地址弄到某个地方
the stack, so that we can use %n with the format string vulnerability.
堆栈，以便我们可以将%n与格式字符串漏洞。
And the issue is that it contains nullbytes which we can’t pass in via the arguments.
问题是它包含空字节我们不能通过参数传递。
I think the arguments are string copied onto the stack?
我认为这些参数是字符串复制到堆栈？
So we can’t enter arbitrary nullbytes.
所以我们不能输入任意的空字节。
But wcbowling had a cool trick with empty strings as arguments.
但是wccolling有一个很酷的空球技巧字符串作为参数。
Because a string ends with a nullbyte, so an empty string is just null.
因为字符串以空字节结尾，所以空字符串仅为空。
I think I had a super early video to talk about the environment and arguments on the
我想我有一个超早期的视频要讲关于环境和关于
stack, but quick recap, you have the argv[] char pointer array, so it’s a list with
叠加，但快速回顾，你有argv[]char指针数组，所以它是一个带有
addresses that point to the strings.
指向字符串的地址。
And then you just have memory with all the strings.
然后你就有了记忆串。
And so this way you can get the address with null-bytes on to the stack.
这样你就可以得到地址堆栈上有空字节。
Pretty clever, I never thought about this before.
很聪明，我从没想过这个以前。
And now you basically just have to put everything together.
现在你基本上只需要把一切一起。
Wcbowling uses pwnlib to implement the exploit, it’s a very useful python library, check
wcBowling使用pwnlib来实现该漏洞，这是一个非常有用的python库，检查
it out.
它出来了。
And so here the magic format string is built with a large offset into the stack that hopefully
因此，这里构建了magic格式字符串在堆栈中有很大的偏移，希望
hits the addresses passed in via the arguments.
点击通过参数传入的地址。
And so there are two single byte writes.
所以有两个单字节的写入。
Why are only two bytes written?
为什么只写两个字节？
well the GOT already contains an address that is almost the target address, except the last
好吧，got已经包含了一个地址几乎是目标地址，除了最后一个
two bytes.
两个字节。
So you can just reuse most of it.
所以你可以重新使用它的大部分。
Then this is being executed in a loop until the winning message is shown.
然后在循环中执行，直到显示获胜消息。
The stack has some randomized offsets, thus you have to try it a few times.
堆栈有一些随机偏移，因此你必须试几次。
Here is the asciicinema recording by wcbowling.
这是wcbowling的电影录音。
By the way, if you have a problem with a challenge and you write me an email, you could use that
顺便说一下，如果你对挑战有问题的话你给我写封电子邮件，你可以用它
to record a screencast so I can actually see how you debug it and what the problem is.
录制一个屏幕放映，这样我才能真正看到如何调试它以及问题是什么。
So while I understand now the basic idea, I still wanted to implement it myself.
所以当我现在明白了基本的想法，我仍然想自己去实现它。
There are a few challenges that you have to solve like, what is good offset into the stack
你必须面对一些挑战解决方法是，什么是好的偏移到堆栈中
to hit the arguments, and the alignment of the address through the arguments.
去打击争论，和通过参数的地址。
And while I was doing that and struggling with exactly those details, I had an epiphany.
当我这样做和挣扎的时候有了这些细节，我顿悟了。
And I’m sooo grateful that wcbowling shared this exploit, because it pushed me into discovering
我很高兴能和你一起打保龄球因为它促使我发现
this.
这个。
So I actually found a 100% reliable exploit for this challenge, and you can’t believe
所以我发现了一个100%可靠的漏洞你不能相信
how excited that makes me.
这让我多么兴奋。
Though I have to admit, that it might only work on my compiled binary, and for somebody
尽管我不得不承认，这可能只是为我编译的二进制文件工作
else it might not work, you will see in a second why.
否则可能不起作用，您将在第二，为什么？
So here it is.
就在这里。
That’s all.
仅此而已。
And when we execute it, you can see it gets into an execution loop of the winning message.
当我们执行它时，你可以看到它进入获胜消息的执行循环。
And while it looks like a simple format string vulnerability with the padding to increase
虽然它看起来像一个简单的格式字符串填充增加的漏洞
the amount of printed characters, an address and a %n or %hn to write to an address, there
打印字符的数量，地址还有一个%n或%hn写到一个地址，那里
are quite a few beautiful puzzle pieces here.
这里有很多漂亮的拼图块。
So the basic idea came, when I was playing around with overwriting the GOT entry for
所以当我玩的时候，基本的想法就出现了重写got条目
__stack_check_fail.
_堆栈检查失败。
wcbowling had two writes and placed the address in the arguments, which made it so unreliable.
wcbowling写了两个字，并把地址在争论中，这使得它如此不可靠。
I thought, maybe we get lucky if we place the address into our string, like I did in
我想，如果我们能把地址输入我们的字符串，就像我在
the last video.
最后一段视频。
But there is one problem.
但有一个问题。
The string that is printed is coming from the arguments, which has an unpredictable
打印的字符串来自参数，它有一个不可预测的
position.
位置。
But the string is formatted with sprintf into a buffer, which will have a fixed relative
但字符串是用sprintf格式化为具有固定相对值的缓冲区
position on our stack.
在我们的堆栈上的位置。
So basically the format string will be evaluated, so first it handles the %d with the 1640 character
所以基本上格式字符串将被计算，所以首先它用1640字符处理%d
padding and places it into the buffer.
填充并将其放入缓冲区。
Then comes the raw bytes of the address, and places it.
然后是地址的原始字节，以及放置它。
And then comes the format modifier to write to an address on the stack.
然后格式修饰符来写到堆栈上的地址。
So now the position of this address that was just written onto the buffer is at a fixed
所以现在这个地址的位置刚刚写入缓冲区的
offset location and we always get it with 214.
偏移位置，我们总是用 214.
Though the problem is, we can’t have an arbitrary amount of bytes padding.
尽管问题是，我们不能任意字节填充量。
Because the address has to be 8byte alligned.
因为地址必须是8字节的联合签名。
So we can only increase or decrease the padding in 8 byte steps.
所以我们只能增加或减少填充8字节步进。
Which affects the amounts of bytes we can write.
这会影响我们可以写。
With %n.
使用%N。
It’s always in these 8 steps.
它总是在这8个步骤。
So we don’t have an write anything condition, but we can write something close to the wiining
所以我们没有写任何条件，但我们可以写一些接近线绳的东西
address.
地址。
Now there are two challenges.
现在有两个挑战。
First, the stack is fairly small, and the format result is written into buffer on the
首先，堆栈相当小，格式结果写入缓冲区
stack, so if we use too much padding, to write a large number with %n, we run out of stack
堆栈，所以如果我们使用了太多的填充来写入一个有%n的大数字，堆栈用完了
memory and get a segfault.
记忆并得到一个SEGAULT。
But wcbowling’s trick has made me realize, that we can in fact increase the size of the
但是wcbowling的技巧让我意识到，我们实际上可以增加
stack by just using more arguments.
通过使用更多参数进行叠加。
It will add entries to the argv array and increase it.
它将向argv数组添加条目，并增加它。
The second problem is, that the address is only written with 3 bytes, so if the location
第二个问题是，地址是只写3个字节，所以如果
on the stack had other values in it, it won’t work.
堆栈中有其他值，但不会工作。
We need to write our address onto the stack where there was a zero, or generally a small
我们需要把地址写在堆栈上如果是零，或者通常是小的
number before.
以前的号码。
And here is also where the arguments help us again, because we can groom the stack,
这也是参数有帮助的地方我们又来了，因为我们可以整理这堆东西，
by adding or remove entries in the argv array, so that the stack is large enough, and we
通过在argv数组中添加或删除条目，这样堆就足够大了，我们
have a zero at the correct spot.
在正确的位置有一个零。
&lt;grunt&gt; I love it!
&lt；grunt&gt；我喜欢它！
So now we know how to groom the stack to write to the GOT entry, but we still have the issue
所以现在我们知道了如何整理堆栈来编写但我们仍然有问题
that we are not sure what to write because of our multiples of 8 restrictions.
我们不知道写什么，因为我们的8倍限制。
I wrote a simple python function that generates me valid exploit arguments with different
我编写了一个简单的python函数，我有效利用不同的参数
paddings and adjusts the amount of arguments and the write offset accordingly.
填充并调整参数的数量以及相应的写偏移量。
And I started by looking around the printing of the winning message.
我先看看印刷品赢的消息。
So ideally we would like to write 0x670, that’s 1648, but becuase of our alignment restrictions
所以理想情况下我们要写0x670，这是1648年，但由于我们的路线限制
that doesn’t work.
那不管用。
Anyway, I was then just trying them, to see if anything interesting would come from it.
不管怎样，当时我只是想试试看如果有什么有趣的事情能从中得到的话。
And luckily this one worked.
幸运的是，这一个成功了。
Let me debug this with gdb, I set a breakpoint after the sprintf, before we check the stack
让我用gdb调试这个，我设置一个断点在sprintf之后，在我们检查堆栈之前
cookie.
饼干。
Let’s look at the stack.
让我们看看这个堆栈。
So this is the %d padding with spaces, to print the amount of characters we want to
这是用空格填充的%d，to打印要打印的字符数
write to.
写信给某人。
And then here at the end is the target address we want to write to.
最后是目标地址我们要写信给。
The GOT address.
得到的地址。
We can also look now what value has been written there.
我们现在也可以看看写了什么值那里。
So we will jump to 0x40066b.
所以我们将跳转到0x40066B。
Let’s look at the disassembly and see where that would be.
让我们看一下分解图，看看在哪里那就是。
66b.
66 B。
Mhmmh… wait!
嗯…等等！
That is not a valid address, this is not right?
地址无效，对吗？
It’s in between the compare and the jump-not-equal.
它在比较和跳跃之间不相等。
Let’s use x to print 3 instructions, instead of the disassemble command.
我们用x来打印3条指令反汇编命令。
Do you see that.
你看到了吗？
WTF there are now moves, and not a cmp?
WTF现在有移动，而不是CMP？
What the heck?
搞什么鬼？
Welcome to intel assembler and more advanced ROP.
欢迎使用Intel汇编程序和更高级的ROP。
This kind of property was called the geometry of intel assembler, in the famous ROP paper,
这种性质被称为几何在著名的ROP论文中，
but never heard anybody using that term.
但从未听人用过这个词。
Anyway, we jump in between the bytes of the intended instruction, and the CPU is dumb,
总之，我们在预期指令，CPU是哑的，
it will just read those bytes and interpret them as assembler.
它只读取这些字节并解释他们是装配工。
And so in this case, the cmp and jne turned into two simple moves.
在这种情况下，CMP和JNE分成两个简单的动作。
Which means, now there is no check for deadbeef and we run into the printf to print the winning
也就是说，现在没有空头支票了我们在印刷品上看到了胜利的图案
message.
消息。
When we single step forward now, we get into the procedure linkage table for stack_check_fail,
当我们向前迈出一步时，我们就进入了堆栈检查失败的过程链接表，
we jump to the GOT entry, which is our weird address into vuln, we execute the mov, and
我们跳到入口，这很奇怪地址输入vuln，我们执行mov，并且
then we call puts to print the message.
然后我们调用Puts来打印消息。